Guide to the Paul Palmer Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Paul Palmer papers
1929-1960
MS 382
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
The papers consist of Paul Palmer's professional correspondence with prominent literary and political figures soliciting articles for publication. In some cases, drafts of articles are included with the letters.
Palmer, Paul, 1900-1983
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Paul Palmer in 1961.
Scope and Contents
This three box collection of approximately five hundred items consists of Paul Palmer's business correspondence, 1923-1960. The majority of the letters are to Palmer from such prominent literary and political figures as: Eli Culbertson, Clarence Darrow, Ford Maddox Ford, Joseph P. Kennedy, John F. Kennedy, Anne Morrow Lindbergh, Charles A. Lindbergh, Henry L. Mencken, John O'Hara and Alexander Woollcott. In some cases drafts of articles were included with the letters, some of these were never published. The letters from Palmer requesting writers to pursue certain topics in articles for publication and the writers' responses to him are revealing. Many of the letters express intelligent opinions, or highly emotional reactions to the various political issues, and thus represent illuminating commentaries on the temper of the times. This collection of papers is a valuable source for research in political and literary thought of the 1930s, 40s and 50s.
Biographical / Historical
Paul Palmer was born in 1900. His career in journalism began in 1922 when he became a reporter for the Baltimore Sun. Between 1923-1926 Palmer was first a reporter, and then Sunday editor of the St. Louis Post Dispatch. He was Sunday editor of the New York World from 1926-1930, and a free-lance writer from 1930-1935. In 1935 Palmer became editor of The American Mercury, a post he held until 1939. From 1939-1941, he was a reporter for Reader's Digest. Palmer was Washington correspondent for the McClure newspaper syndicate during 1941. In 1942 he returned to Reader's Digest and became a senior editor. Paul Palmer died on July 2, 1983.
Journalism; United States -- Intellectual life -- 20th Century; Editors; Journalists; Culbertson, Ely, 1891-1955; Darrow, Clarence, 1857-1938; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963; Kennedy, Joseph P. (Joseph Patrick), 1888-1969; Kenney, George C. (George Churchill), 1889-1977; Lindbergh, Anne Morrow, 1906-2001; Lindbergh, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1902-1974; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956; Nock, Albert Jay, 1872 or 1873-1945; O'Hara, John, 1905-1970; Palmer, Paul, 1900-1983; Woollcott, Alexander, 1887-1943
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - Altieri, James, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Acheson, Dean Gooderham, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Amory, Cleveland, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Anderson, Sherwood, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Atherton, John C., 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Austin, Warren Robinson, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bacher, Robert Fox, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Barmine, Alexander G., 1940, 1944, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Barnes, Harry Elmer, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Baruch, Bernard Mannes, 1939, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Beach, Rex Ellingwood, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Beard, Charles Austin, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Beaverbrook, William Maxwell Aitken, 1955-1956, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Belasco, David, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bellamy, Paul, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bellco, Hilaire, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Bent, William Rose, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Bey, Richard, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Borchard, Edwin Montefiore, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Boyd, James, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Bradley, Omar Nelson, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Brandeis, Louis Dembitz, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Bricker, John William, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Bromfield, Louis, 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Broun, Heywood Campbell, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Browder, Earl Russell, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Buck, Pearl S., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Bullitt, William C., 1944, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Burke, Arleigh A., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Burnham, James, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Bynner, Witter, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Byrd, Harry Flood, 1939, 1942, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Cabell, James Branch, 1929, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Cain, James Mallahan, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Catchings, Waddill, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Cather, Willa S., undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Chamberlin, William H., 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - _____, Christine, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Churchill, Allen, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Churchill, Winston, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Clark, Bennett Champ, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Cleugh, James, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Cline, Leonard, 1923-1925 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Cobb, Irvin S., 1928 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Connelly, Marc, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Conolly, Richard L., 1949 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Coolidge, Calvin, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Copeland, Charles T., undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Corcoran, Thomas G., 1940 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Cousins, Norman, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Cram, Ralph Adams, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Crowninshield, Francis W., 1934 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Culbertson, Ely, 1942-1954 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Daniels, Josephus, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Darrow, Clarence S., 1930 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Darwin, Charles G., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Davies, Joseph E., 1942 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Dawson, Coningsby W., 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Dell, Floyd, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - De Seversky, Alexander P., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Devoe, Alan, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - De Voto, Bernard A., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Dewey, Thomas E., 1939, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Diat, Louis, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Dimnet, Ernest, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Dobie, Charles C., 1929 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Dreiser, Theodore, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Duranty, Walter, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Eastman, Max, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Einstein, Albert, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Ellis, Havelock, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Errante, Guido, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Erskine, John, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Farson, Negley, undated (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Faulkner, William, undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Ferber, Edna, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Ferguson, Charles W., undated (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Ferragamo, Salvatore, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Fitzgerald, F. Scott, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Fitzpatrick, Daniel R., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Flynn, John T., 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Ford, Ford Maddox, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Ford, Janice, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Forrestal, James, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Frohman, Daniel, undated (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - Gale, Zona, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Galsworthy, John, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Gest, Morris, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Gibbons, Floyd Phillips, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Gibbs, Sir Philip H., 1929 (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - Gogarty, Oliver St. J., 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - Green, William, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 94)
    - Grey, Zane, undated (Box 1, Folder 95)
    - Hanes, John W., 1939, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 96)
    - Harris, Eleanor, undated (Box 1, Folder 97)
    - Hergesheimer, Joseph, 1929, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 98)
    - Holbrook, Stewart H., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 99)
    - Hoover, Herbert, 1941, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 100)
    - Hoover, J. Edgar, 1940, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 101)
    - Hopkins, Arthur M., 1944 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Hughes, Llewellyn, undated (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Hughes, Rupert, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Hurst, Fannie, undated (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Hutchins, Robert M., 1949 (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - Joanna of Bulgaria, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 107)
    - Johnson, Louis A., 1949 (Box 2, Folder 108)
    - Jouvenel, Bertrand de, 1948-1952 (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - Kalb, Marvin L., 1959 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Kaufman, George S., undated (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Kelland, Clarence B., 1929 (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - Kennan, George F., 1949 (Box 2, Folder 113)
    - Kennedy, John F., 1944, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 114)
    - Kennedy, Joseph P., 1943-1945, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 115)
    - Kenney, George C., 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 116)
    - King, Ernest J., 1940 (Box 2, Folder 117)
    - Kirby, Rollin, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - Knopf, Alfred A., 1939 (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Knudsen, William S., 1940 (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - Krock, Arthur, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - Krueger, Karl, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - Kyne, Peter B., 1929 (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - Lamont, Thomas W., 1939 (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - Lansing, Alfred, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 125)
    - Leacock, Stephen Butler, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - Lederer, William J., 1959 (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - Levine, Isaac Don, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 128)
    - Levy, Newman, undated (Box 2, Folder 129)
    - Lewis, C. I., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 130)
    - Lewis, Sinclair, 1929, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 131)
    - Lilienthal, David E., 1950 (Box 2, Folder 132)
    - Lin, Yu-T'ang, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 133)
    - Lindbergh, Anne Morrow, 1945-1955 (Box 2, Folder 134)
    - Lindbergh, Charles A., 1942-1957 (Box 2, Folder 135)
    - Lindsay, Howard, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 136)
    - Lippmann, Walter, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 137)
    - Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 138)
    - Long, Breckinridge, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 139)
    - Loos, Anita, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 140)
    - Lothian, Philip H.K., 1940 (Box 2, Folder 141)
    - Lovett, Robert A., 1948 (Box 2, Folder 142)
    - Luce, Clare Boothe, 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 143)
    - Luckner, Felix, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 144)
    - Ludwig, Emil, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 145)
    - Lundeen, Ernest, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 146)
    - Lunt, Storer B., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 147)
    - McFee, William, 1927, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 148)
    - McMein, Neysa, undated (Box 2, Folder 149)
    - McNary, Charles L., 1939 (Box 2, Folder 150)
    - Malone, Dumas, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 151)
    - Mann, Thomas, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 152)
    - Marías, Julián, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 153)
    - Marquand, John P., 1943 (Box 2, Folder 154)
    - Marshall, George Catlett, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 155)
    - Martin, John Bartlow, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 156)
    - Masefield, John, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 157)
    - Masters, Edgar Lee, 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 158)
    - Maugham, William Somerset, undated (Box 2, Folder 159)
    - Maurois, Andr, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 160)
    - Mencken, Henry L., 1924, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 161)
    - Merz, Charles, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 162)
    - Michelson, Charles, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 163)
    - Middleton, George, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 164)
    - Miller, Mrs. Alice, undated (Box 2, Folder 165)
    - Montgomery, Bernard L., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 166)
    - Morgenstern, Oskar, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 167)
    - Morley, Christopher, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 168)
    - Nagy, Ferenc, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 169)
    - Nason, Leonard H., undated (Box 2, Folder 170)
    - Neeley, M. M., 1940 (Box 2, Folder 171)
    - Nevins, Allan Nock, Albert J., 1954 (Box 2, Folder 172)
      General
      (See: Nock Collection)
    - Norris, Charles G., 1929 (Box 2, Folder 173)
    - Noyes, Newbold, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 174)
    - Nye, Gerald P., 1939 (Box 2, Folder 175)
    - O'Hara, John, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 176)
    - Ortega y Gasset, Jos, 1949-1954 (Box 2, Folder 177)
    - Oursler, Fulton, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 178)
    - Padev, Michael A., 1960 (Box 2, Folder 179)
    - Pearce, Charles A., 1959 (Box 2, Folder 180)
    - Pegler, Westbrook, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 181)
    - Pemberton, Brock, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 182)
    - Pershing, John Joseph, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 183)
    - Pfeiffer, Karl G., 1961 (Box 2, Folder 184)
    - Pittman, Key, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 185)
    - Pollock, Channing, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 186)
    - Pulitzer, Joseph Jr., 1940 (Box 2, Folder 187)
    - Quarles, Donald A., 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 188)
    - Quezon, Manuel Luis, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 189)
    - Rand, Ayn, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 190)
    - Regnery, Henry, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 191)
    - Rhine, Joseph Banks, 1955, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 192)
    - Rockefeller, Winthrop, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 193)
    - Romains, Jules, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 194)
    - Romand, Michael, undated (Box 2, Folder 195)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 196)
    - Roosevelt, Nicholas, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 197)
    - Ross, Harold Wallace, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 198)
    - Ruark, Robert, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 199)
    - Russell, Bertrand, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 200)
    - Russell, Doria, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 201)
    - Scott, Jack Denton, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 202)
    - Shaw, George Bernard, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 203)
    - Sheridan, Mrs. Clare Consuelo, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 204)
    - Smith, Alfred Emanuel, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 205)
    - Stallings, Laurence, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 206)
    - Starr, John, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 207)
    - Stevens, James, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 208)
    - Stewart, Donald Ogden, undated (Box 3, Folder 209)
    - Stokes, Richard L., 1954 (Box 3, Folder 210)
    - Stowe, Leland, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 211)
    - Straus, Roger William, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 212)
    - Strauss, Lewis L., 1951 (Box 3, Folder 213)
    - Stuart, Jesse, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 214)
    - Stuhldreher, Harry A., 1934 (Box 3, Folder 215)
    - Sullivan, Mark, undated (Box 3, Folder 216)
    - Swope, Herbert, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 217)
    - Symington, William Stuart, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 218)
    - Taft, Robert A., 1939 (Box 3, Folder 219)
    - Tarkington, Susan, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 220)
    - Thomas, Albert E., undated (Box 3, Folder 221)
    - Thomas, Lowell J., 1929, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 222)
    - Thomason, John W., 1939-1943 (Box 3, Folder 223)
    - Thompson, Dorothy, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 224)
    - Towne, Charles H., 1929 (Box 3, Folder 225)
    - Trotskii, Lev, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 226)
    - Tunney, Gene, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 227)
    - T_____ (unidentified), undated (Box 3, Folder 228)
    - Underwood, Mrs. Sophie Kerr, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 229)
    - Vandenberg, Arthur H., 1944 (Box 3, Folder 230)
    - Vandenberg, Hoyt S., 1951 (Box 3, Folder 231)
    - Van Dine, S. S., 1929 (Box 3, Folder 232)
    - Van Loon, Hendrick Willem, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 233)
    - Wallace, Edgar, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 234)
    - Wallace, Henry A., 1940, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 235)
    - Walsh, David I., 1941 (Box 3, Folder 236)
    - Weaver, Richard M., 1948 (Box 3, Folder 237)
    - Wedemeyer, Albert C., 1950 (Box 3, Folder 238)
    - Wells, Herbert, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 239)
    - White, Stewart E., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 240)
    - White, William A., 1929 (Box 3, Folder 241)
    - Willkie, Wendell L., 1939, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 242)
    - Wilson, Neill C., 1958 (Box 3, Folder 243)
    - Wolfe, Reese, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 244)
    - Woollcott, Alexander, 1928, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 245)
    - Wylie, Ida A. R., undated (Box 3, Folder 246)
    - Wylie, Philip, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 247)
    - unidentified, 1946, undated (Box 3, Folder 248)